<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>mridoni&#x27;s development blog</title>
    <link href="https://mridoni.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://mridoni.github.io" />
    <updated>2023-01-03T18:11:30+01:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Marco Ridoni</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://mridoni.github.io</id>

    <entry>
        <title>January update</title>
        <author>
            <name>Marco Ridoni</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mridoni.github.io/january-update.html"/>
        <id>https://mridoni.github.io/january-update.html</id>

        <updated>2023-01-03T18:11:30+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Happy New Year! The work on GixSQL is progressing and v1.0.20 is on the operating table (or on the assembly line, depending on your metaphor of choice). I have pushed the corresponding branch on GitHub and I am updating it regularly. GixSQL v1.0.20 will see not only new features and fixes, but also a notable number of modifications to improve memory usage and reliability: the codebase has been almost totally moved from its C origins&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Happy New Year! The work on GixSQL is progressing and v1.0.20 is on the operating table (or on the assembly line, depending on your metaphor of choice). I have pushed the corresponding <a href="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/tree/v1.0.20dev" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">branch on GitHub</a> and I am updating it regularly.</p>
<p>GixSQL v1.0.20 will see not only new features and fixes, but also a notable number of modifications to improve memory usage and reliability: the codebase has been almost totally moved from its C origins and migrated (sort of) to more modern C++ constructs.</p>
<p>The test suite has been modified and, being written in C#/.Net Core, can also be easily run on Linux. The corresponding documentation on how to use and extend it will be provided in the release. Moreover, the test suite can also be run in GitHub Actions (or locally with <a href="https://github.com/nektos/act" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ACT</a>) and provides a hook to run the tests under Valgrind (on LInux) or DrMemory (on Windows).</p>
<p>I still have not set a release date or an ETA for the <a href="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/milestone/1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">v1.0.20 milestone</a>, it will reasonably take me a couple more weeks - barring unforeseen problems and work commitments - to see how the work is going and give an estimate; I simply don't want to say "X weeks" when it is going to take "Y".</p>
<p>You can check the current progress on the <a href="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/milestone/1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">v1.0.20 milestone page</a>: issues that are technically "closed" in the branch but still open for some reason (mainly the need for more tests or the fact that they will need some modification along the line due to the integration of the code for a different issue) are marked as "ready".</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Gix-IDE v1.1.1 is out</title>
        <author>
            <name>Marco Ridoni</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mridoni.github.io/gix-ide-v111-is-out.html"/>
        <id>https://mridoni.github.io/gix-ide-v111-is-out.html</id>

        <updated>2022-12-19T15:11:24+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This is a release for Gix-IDE that improves on 1.1.1 and fixes a few problems. The "standard" debugger is still the recommended one, but the "experimental" version is functional both on Windows and Linux. This release also arrives with new binary packages for Debian 10 and 11. Binary packages available A summary of new features and fixes Known bugs and issues Available, as usual, on the Release page on GitHub. As usual, donations or sponsors are welcome.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>This is a release for Gix-IDE that improves on 1.1.1 and fixes a few problems. The "standard" debugger is still the recommended one, but the "experimental" version is functional both on Windows and Linux.</p>
<p>This release also arrives with new binary packages for Debian 10 and 11.</p>
<p><strong>Binary packages available</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Windows x86</li>
<li>Windows x64</li>
<li>Linux x64 (Ubuntu 20.04LTS)</li>
<li>Linux x64 (Ubuntu 22.04LTS)</li>
<li>Linux x64 (Debian 10)</li>
<li>Linux x64 (Debian 11)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>A summary of new features and fixes</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The IDE logging system is now based on spdlog</li>
<li>The output window has been split into different panes</li>
<li>Added clickable "Error List" window</li>
<li>Linux debugger fixes</li>
<li>Added packages for Debian 10 and 11</li>
<li>The Linux version can now automatically use a distribution-provided install of GnuCOBOL</li>
<li>Fixed a linking problem for GixSQL when used with a MinGW compiler from the IDE</li>
<li>Fixed ESQL sample project</li>
<li>On Windows the user can now decide whether to install the MSVC runtime locally or globally</li>
<li>The Windows installer does not require administrative privileges anymore (still needed for VC++ Build Tools)</li>
<li>Removed some test-related dead code</li>
<li>In the IDE, files can now be dragged and dropped on a project folder</li>
<li>Added filename tooltips on editor tabs</li>
<li>On Linux the correct scaling factor is now used on a fresh install</li>
<li>Internal fixes in GixSQL for metadata handling</li>
<li>Fixed ESQL parameter-style setting in the IDE (now it is possible to set the corect parameter style/prefix).</li>
<li>Added an option in the IDE that maps to GixSQL's "consolidate source" (i.e. stitch all module sources/COPY files together before preprocessing). This is needed in some scenarios to properly parse metadata.</li>
<li>Fixed a possible crash in the logging system</li>
<li>gix-http was inadvertently deactivated in the build configuration, now it is built again by default</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Known bugs and issues</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The new Output/Error windows still have some small quirks (some messages not being displayed, UI glitches, etc.).</li>
</ul>
<p>Available, as usual, on the <a href="https://github.com/mridoni/gix/releases/tag/v1.1.0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Release page</a> on GitHub.</p>
<p>As usual, <a href="https://paypal.me/mridoni" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">donations </a>or <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/mridoni" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">sponsors</a> are welcome.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Gix-IDE: December update</title>
        <author>
            <name>Marco Ridoni</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mridoni.github.io/gix-ide-early-december-update.html"/>
        <id>https://mridoni.github.io/gix-ide-early-december-update.html</id>

        <updated>2022-12-19T15:08:08+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    In the last few days I have committed several improvements and fixes to GitHub. New features and fixes Known bugs and issues All of this will be part of a v1.1.1 release that should be available after the necessary testing phase, probably in a week or two, surely before the Christmas holidays. As usual, donations or sponsors are welcome.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>In the last few days I have committed several improvements and fixes to GitHub.</p>
<p><strong>New features and fixes</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>An "Error List" window has been added, to display build errors and warnings. When double-clicking an error message, the editor will switch to the file and line indicated.</li>
<li>The output window was split into different panes ("IDE", "Build" and "Debug", for now) so that the output of different subsystem can be routed in a proper way and be less confusing. This should fix issue #113 and #126, or at least be a rather big step in that direction.</li>
<li>The logging system in the IDE is now based on <a href="https://github.com/gabime/spdlog" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">spdlog</a>, QLogger usage is confined (for now) to <code>gix-http</code>.</li>
<li>Metadata management has been fixed and made faster.</li>
<li>The build system received a few fixes. Multi-binary projects now work correctly (this should also solve #112).</li>
<li>Filename tooltips have been added to the editor tabs</li>
<li>Files can now be also dragged onto project folders, not just on the projects themselves</li>
<li>The Windows installers do not need administrative rights anymore. If a non-administrative user chooses to install a MSVC-based version of GnuCOBOL, a warning will be displayed (Visual Studio 2022 C++ Build Tools need administrative rights to be installed, no way around that). The user can choose whether to go back or to continue. If the latter option is chosen, the customary rights elevation prompt will be displayed when trying to install the Visual Studio 2022 C++ Build Tools.</li>
<li>Fixed ESQL parameter-style setting in the IDE (now it is possible to set the corect parameter style/prefix).</li>
<li>Added an option in the IDE that maps to GixSQL's "consolidate source" (i.e. stitch all module sources/COPY files together before preprocessing). This is needed in some scenarios to properly parse metadata.</li>
<li>Fixed a possible crash in the logging system</li>
<li><code>gix-http </code>was inadvertently deactivated in the build configuration, now it is built again by default</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Known bugs and issues</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The new Output/Error windows still have some small quirks (some messages not being displayed, UI glitches, etc.). I hope to solve them before the release, but since the new logging/output system is a massive improvement over the older one and the way to go, it will be shipped anyway.</li>
<li>I still have not decided whether to install "in place" the MSVC runtime files for GixSQL runtime libraries. While not a big issue for the GixSQL version shipped with Gix-IDE, this might have an adverse effect on production systems where an updated MSVC runtime is available and regularly updated at system level.</li>
</ul>
<p>All of this will be part of a v1.1.1 release that should be available after the necessary testing phase, probably in a week or two, surely before the Christmas holidays.</p>
<p>As usual, <a href="https://paypal.me/mridoni" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">donations </a>or <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/mridoni" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">sponsors</a> are welcome.</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Gix-IDE 1.1.0 is available</title>
        <author>
            <name>Marco Ridoni</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mridoni.github.io/gix-ide-110-is-available.html"/>
        <id>https://mridoni.github.io/gix-ide-110-is-available.html</id>

        <updated>2022-12-07T17:27:13+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This is a release for Gix-IDE that integrates the new "standalone" debugger engine and consolidates the various development (internal) branches. While the "standard" debugger is still the one to be currently used, having a single and published version will help speed up the development process. This release also arrives with new binary packages: compiler and runtime files have been moved outside the installer itself and will be downloaded on-demand. While this means that an Internet&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>This is a release for Gix-IDE that integrates the new "standalone" debugger engine and consolidates the various development (internal) branches. While the "standard" debugger is still the one to be currently used, having a single and published version will help speed up the development process.</p>
<p>This release also arrives with new binary packages: compiler and runtime files have been moved outside the installer itself and will be downloaded on-demand. While this means that an Internet connection is needed to install Gix-IDE with a compiler, it makes the installer a lot smaller and more easily upgradable. As a consequence, there are no more "no-compilers" packages, you just will just have to skip installing the compiler(s) when running the installer.</p>
<p>Moreover, the Windows binary installers have been signed with my code-signing certificate, for an added level of trust.</p>
<p>There is a brand-new package for Ubuntu 22.04, that should avoid the compatibility hacks that were needed for the previous package (aimed at 20.04). Debian-specific packages will follow as soon as possible.</p>
<p>Since this is the first release of a new cycle (a so-called ".0") there are probably a few bugs - both in packaging and in the code itself - that have to be shaken down, and a few known issues (see below), but as development is gaining some traction, I really needed to streamline the process, and this release is a step in that (hopefully right) direction.</p>
<p>Another point of attention is the fact that the new packages are being built with GitHub Actions: the building and packaging process is entirely reproducible using the workflows supplied in this repository. This also means that - internally - development has been moved entirely from a SVN-based setup to Git/GitHub: some long-term work will still take place internally (at first), but updates on GitHub will be quicker and more frequent.</p>
<p>All of the above (building, packaging, etc.), starting from the next release (v1.0.19), also apply to GixSQL, for which I am doing some planning/research and hope to have a more accurate timeframe really soon.</p>
<p>By the way: I have added a new e-mail address to my key because I started to sign the binary installers with a code signing certificate, and it just seemed "prettier" to use for the e-mail contact a domain that I own instead of a generic GMail address.</p>
<p>Binary packages available</p>
<ul>
<li>Windows x86</li>
<li>Windows x64</li>
<li>Linux x64 (Ubuntu 20.04LTS)</li>
<li>Linux x64 (Ubuntu 22.04LTS)</li>
</ul>
<p>A summary of new features and fixes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Integrated "standalone" debugger (still not completely functional)</li>
<li>Enabled rectangular selection in the editor</li>
<li>Added tooltips for COBOL variables in the editor with variable information (the content of a variable is also displayed when debugging)</li>
<li>ESQL blocks are now automatically skipped when debugging (the debugger stops on the first line of the block, then "jumps" after the END-EXEC clause when stepping</li>
<li>Added new icons (including for file types used by Gix-IDE)</li>
<li>Linux build and debugger fixes</li>
</ul>
<p>Known bugs and issues</p>
<ul>
<li>The standalone debugger is present but it is still a work in progress, so some things might not work as expected (e.g. debugging when using a MinGW-based compiler on Windows). The debugger version can be selected under Settings -&gt; Debug</li>
<li>When debugging on Windows, a "stray" console window appear, this is probably from some logging artifact</li>
</ul>
<p>Available, as usual, on the <a href="https://github.com/mridoni/gix/releases/tag/v1.1.0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Release page</a> on GitHub.</p>
<p><a href="https://paypal.me/mridoni" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Donations </a>or <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/mridoni" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">sponsors</a> are welcome.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>GixSQL 1.0.19 is out</title>
        <author>
            <name>Marco Ridoni</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mridoni.github.io/gixsql-1019-is-out.html"/>
        <id>https://mridoni.github.io/gixsql-1019-is-out.html</id>

        <updated>2022-12-07T17:27:27+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This is a new release for GixSQL, that mainly re-implements autocommit and updatable cursor support, and fixes a few bugs. For information on how these two features work, look at the (updated) documentation, where a specific section has been added. A point of attention is the fact that the new packages are being built with GitHub Actions: the building and packaging process is entirely reproducible using the workflows supplied in the repository. This also means&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>This is a new release for GixSQL, that mainly re-implements autocommit and updatable cursor support, and fixes a few bugs. For information on how these two features work, look at the (updated) documentation, where a specific section has been added.</p>
<p>A point of attention is the fact that the new packages are being built with GitHub Actions: the building and packaging process is entirely reproducible using the workflows supplied in the repository. This also means that - internally - development has been moved entirely from a SVN-based setup to Git/GitHub: some long-term work will still take place internally (at first), but updates on GitHub will be quicker and more frequent.</p>
<p><em>Note: I have added a new e-mail address to my key because I started to sign the binary installers with a code signing certificate, and it just seemed "prettier" to use for the e-mail contact a domain that I own instead of a generic GMail address.</em></p>
<p>Binary packages available</p>
<ul>
<li>Windows x64 (MSVC + MinGW)</li>
<li>Windows x64 (MinGW only)</li>
<li>Windows x86 (MSVC + MinGW)</li>
<li>Windows x86 (MinGW only)</li>
<li>Windows x86 "portable"</li>
<li>Linux x64 (Ubuntu 20.04)</li>
</ul>
<p>There is also a autoconf-enabled source package, to make building on Linux and MinGW easier.</p>
<p>A summary of new features and fixes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Re-implemented autocommit and updatable cursor support (also affects <a class="issue-link js-issue-link" data-error-text="Failed to load title" data-id="1205386006" data-permission-text="Title is private" data-url="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/issues/14" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/mridoni/gixsql/issues/14/hovercard" href="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/issues/14">#14</a>)</li>
<li>Docs and examples are now included in the autoconf tarball (fixes <a class="issue-link js-issue-link" data-error-text="Failed to load title" data-id="1244202721" data-permission-text="Title is private" data-url="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/issues/50" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/mridoni/gixsql/issues/50/hovercard" href="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/issues/50">#50</a>)</li>
<li>Changed cursor state ownership (fixes <a class="issue-link js-issue-link" data-error-text="Failed to load title" data-id="1350462043" data-permission-text="Title is private" data-url="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/issues/115" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/mridoni/gixsql/issues/115/hovercard" href="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/issues/115">#115</a>)</li>
<li>Fix for "parser error on semicolon and error continuation does not work" (<a class="issue-link js-issue-link" data-error-text="Failed to load title" data-id="1354513480" data-permission-text="Title is private" data-url="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/issues/118" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/mridoni/gixsql/issues/118/hovercard" href="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/issues/118">#118</a>)</li>
</ul>
<p>Availaible, as usual, on the <a href="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/releases/tag/v1.0.19" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Release page</a> on GitHub.</p>
<p><a href="https://paypal.me/mridoni" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Donations </a>or <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/mridoni" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">sponsors</a> are welcome.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>GixSQL: news about v1.0.19</title>
        <author>
            <name>Marco Ridoni</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mridoni.github.io/gixsql-news-about-v1019.html"/>
        <id>https://mridoni.github.io/gixsql-news-about-v1019.html</id>

        <updated>2022-11-18T12:25:04+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The internal branch v1.0.19dev has been merged into main and it will be the base for the upcoming version v1.0.19. It implements, as announced, support for autocommit and updatable cursors. It includes, obviously, some fixes that have been applied to the main branch in past few weeks. This merge will also allow to integrate fixes for other issues more easily. The final release of v1.0.19 should be out in a week, two at most, then&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>The internal branch v1.0.19dev has been merged into main and it will be the base for the upcoming version v1.0.19. It implements, as <a href="https://mridoni.github.io/gixsql-mid-november-update.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">announced</a>, support for autocommit and updatable cursors. It includes, obviously, some fixes that have been applied to the main branch in past few weeks.</p>
<p>This merge will also allow to integrate fixes for other issues more easily. The final release of v1.0.19 should be out in a week, two at most, then - barring the need for hotfixes - work will resume on Gix-IDE with two main targets: complete functionality for the standalone debugger and an enhanced error/output window.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>GixSQL: Mid-November update</title>
        <author>
            <name>Marco Ridoni</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mridoni.github.io/gixsql-mid-november-update.html"/>
        <id>https://mridoni.github.io/gixsql-mid-november-update.html</id>

        <updated>2022-11-16T19:23:23+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    GixSQL is undergoing some work to re-implement two features: autocommit support and updatable cursors. Both of them have been there since the first releases, but due to several reasons (essentially lack of usage and bad assumptions) they were left behind and their functionality, in their current incarnation, is dubious. The new implementation sees these two features being moved mainly from the main library (libgixsql) to the database driver libraries (e.g. libgixsql-pgsql), with only a few&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>GixSQL is undergoing some work to re-implement two features: autocommit support and updatable cursors. Both of them have been there since the first releases, but due to several reasons (essentially lack of usage and bad assumptions) they were left behind and their functionality, in their current incarnation, is dubious.</p>
<p>The new implementation sees these two features being moved mainly from the main library (libgixsql) to the database driver libraries (e.g. libgixsql-pgsql), with only a few parameters passed around. The rationale behind this move is that different DBMSs behave in different ways, and trying to keep a unified approach would only lead to confusion (and bugs, a lot of bugs). What follows is the level of support planned for the various DB drivers.</p>
<h4>Autocommit</h4>
<p>Autocommit will basically work in three different modes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Native: the connection will start in the default mode used by the database</li>
<li>On: a <code>COMMIT </code>will be executed after each successful statement</li>
<li>Off: the connection will start by opening a transaction. A new connection will be started after each <code>COMMIT </code>and <code>ROLLBACK</code></li>
</ul>
<p>Driver notes:</p>
<ul>
<li>MySQL and ODBC (through its own drivers) directly support autocommit to be turned on or off, so the handling of this feature will be passed entirely to the native driver (e.g. libmysqlclient)</li>
<li>Oracle has no concept of autocommit, just as PostgreSQL, but the first one always work in transaction mode, while transactions must be explicitly started in PostgreSQL. While autocommit (or "transaction mode" in the case of PostgreSQL) have been - and will further be - tested, these differences (and the ones above) can probably lead to different behaviours when switching a single codebase that makes heavy use of the autocommit feature to a different DB, if precautions are not taken and tests performed.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Updatable cursors</h4>
<p>Updatable cursors will allow the update/deletion of a single cursor row after a fetch, using the clause <code>UPDATE...WHERE CURRENT OF mycursor </code>after a cursor has been opened <code>FOR UPDATE</code>.</p>
<p>Driver notes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Oracle directly supports updatable cursors, so the handling of this feature will be passed entirely to the native driver.</li>
<li>PostgreSQL directly supports updatable cursors when native cursors are enabled - this is the default - in the GixSQL driver (libgixsql-pgsql); in this case the handling of this feature will be passed entirely to the native driver. If cursors are emulated in PostgreSQL, updatable cursors are not available.</li>
<li>MySQL and SQLite have updatable cursor emulation: the table on which the cursor is opened must have a unique key that will be used for the update. This has been proven to work, but it is obviously (a lot) slower than native support.</li>
<li>ODBC will defer updatable cursor handling to its own drivers: it depends on them whether updatable cursors will be available or not. As a side note the ODBC driver for MySQL (MySQL Connector/ODBC) uses the same technique illustrated above to emulate updatable cursors.</li>
</ul>
<p>While this is the focus of what will be v1.0.19 (some prereleases will surely be published before that) there will be the usual amount of bug fixes and, where possible, smaller features.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Gix-IDE v1.1.0dev1 (pre-release) is out</title>
        <author>
            <name>Marco Ridoni</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mridoni.github.io/gix-ide-v110dev1-pre-release-is-out.html"/>
        <id>https://mridoni.github.io/gix-ide-v110dev1-pre-release-is-out.html</id>

        <updated>2022-11-07T18:11:16+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This is a pre-release for Gix-IDE that integrates the new "standalone" debugger engine and consolidates the various development (internal) branches. While the "standard" debugger is the one to be currently used, having a single and published version will help speed up the development process. This pre-release also arrives with new binary packages: compiler and runtime files have been moved outside the installer itself and will be downloaded on-demand. While this means that an Internet connection is&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>This is a pre-release for Gix-IDE that integrates the new "standalone" debugger engine and consolidates the various development (internal) branches. While the "standard" debugger <strong>is</strong> the one to be currently used, having a single and published version will help speed up the development process.</p>
<p>This pre-release also arrives with new binary packages: compiler and runtime files have been moved outside the installer itself and will be downloaded on-demand. While this means that an Internet connection is needed to install Gix-IDE <em>with</em> a compiler, it makes the installer a lot smaller and more easily upgradable. As a consequence, there are no more "no-compilers" packages, you just will just have to skip installing the compiler(s) when running the installer.</p>
<p>Moreover, the Windows binary packages have been signed with my code-signing certificate, for an added level of trust.</p>
<p>There is a brand-new package for Ubuntu 22.04, that should avoid the compatibility hacks that were needed for the previous package (aimed at 20.04). Debian-specific packages will follow as soon as possible.</p>
<p>Beware: this pre-release is to be considered of "beta quality": there are probably a few bugs - both in packaging and in the code itself - that have to be shaken down, and a few known issues (see below), but as development is gaining some traction, I really needed to streamline the process, and this (pre-)release is a step in that direction.</p>
<p>Another point of attention is the fact that the new packages are being built with GitHub Actions: the building and packaging process is entirely reproducible using the workflows supplied in this repository. This also means that - internally - development has been moved almost entirely from a SVN-based setup to Git/GitHub: some long-term work will still take place internally (at first), but updates on GitHub will be quicker and more frequent.</p>
<p>All of the above (building, packaging, etc.), starting from the next release, will also apply to GixSQL, for which I am doing some planning/research and hope to have a timeframe really soon.</p>
<p>The packages are signed with my GPG private key. The corresponding public key (<a href="mailto:m.ridoni@gmail.com">m.ridoni@gmail.com</a>, fingerprint 70E4 08CF B89B 5FA8 32E4 5292 EFDC 94BD 5260 B939) has been published on pgp.mit.edu and keyserver.ubuntu.com and is available at <a href="https://github.com/mridoni.gpg">https://github.com/mridoni.gpg</a></p>
<p>Binary packages available</p>
<ul>
<li>Windows x86</li>
<li>Windows x64</li>
<li>Linux x64 (Ubuntu 20.04LTS)</li>
<li>Linux x64 (Ubuntu 22.04LTS)</li>
</ul>
<p>A summary of new features and fixes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Integrated "standalone" debugger (still not completely functional)</li>
<li>Enabled rectangular selection in the editor</li>
<li>Added tooltips for COBOL variables in the editor with variable information (the content of a variable is also displayed when debugging)</li>
<li>ESQL blocks are now automatically skipped when debugging (the debugger stops on the first line of the block, then "jumps" after the END-EXEC clause when stepping</li>
<li>Added new icons (including for file types used by Gix-IDE)</li>
<li>Linux build and debugger fixes</li>
</ul>
<p>Known bugs and issues</p>
<ul>
<li>The standalone debugger is present but still not functional. The next step, of course, will be enabling it. If you <em>really</em> want to try, the debugger version can be selected under Settings -&gt; Debug</li>
<li>When debugging on Windows, a "stray" console window appear, this is probably from some logging artifact</li>
</ul>
<p>As usual, the release is <a href="https://github.com/mridoni/gix/releases/tag/v1.1.0dev1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">available on GitHub</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>&quot;New debugger&quot; source available</title>
        <author>
            <name>Marco Ridoni</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mridoni.github.io/new-debugger-source-available.html"/>
        <id>https://mridoni.github.io/new-debugger-source-available.html</id>

        <updated>2022-10-30T09:39:46+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The new-debugger branch has been merged into main on GitHub. The corresponding binary packages will be available in a few days with a new pre-release (most likely as v1.1.0dev1). The packaging process is almost complete: the workflows included in the repository can already be used to build the binary packages, but there are still a few details I want to iron out before distributing the packages: this will still be a pre-release and it's a&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>The <em>new-debugger</em> branch has been merged into <em>main </em>on GitHub. The corresponding binary packages will be available in a few days with a new pre-release (most likely as v1.1.0dev1). </p>
<p>The packaging process is almost complete: the workflows included in the repository can already be used to build the binary packages, but there are still a few details I want to iron out before distributing the packages: this will still be a pre-release and it's a milestone that will help me to streamline the development process, but obviously I would like it to push it out without major bugs or blocking issues.</p>
<p>The Windows binary packages will also be signed, for the first time, with a code signing certificate. I really dislike the practices that seem rampant in the "security industry", with prices that seem to bear no relation to the actual product <span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">b</span><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">eing sold </span><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">(including the identity verification, not just the certificate). </span>Nevertheless, since Gix-IDE is not-so-easy to build and package for ordinary users, and the SmartScreen alert on Windows had some people justifiably worried, I decided to bite the bullet.</p>
<p><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Side note: I sincerely hope that someone at SigStore (and Microsoft) comes to the realization that software does not mean only containers and images but also old-fashioned software packages. To be clear: SigStore is great but, in my very own opinion, its lack of attention (so far) towards a great part of the computing world, apart from making it useless in many cases, is a disappointment.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>GixSQL v1.0.18b is out</title>
        <author>
            <name>Marco Ridoni</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://mridoni.github.io/gixsql-v1018b-is-out.html"/>
        <id>https://mridoni.github.io/gixsql-v1018b-is-out.html</id>

        <updated>2022-10-27T17:49:28+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This is a "hotfix" release for GixSQL, that fixes a few issues. Available binary packages: There is also a autoconf-enabled source package, to make building on Linux and MinGW easier. A summary of new features and fixes: All the binary packages are available, as usual, on the corresponding Release page on GitHub.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>This is a "hotfix" release for GixSQL, that fixes a few issues. </p>
<p>Available binary packages:</p>
<ul>
<li>Windows x64 (MSVC + MinGW)</li>
<li>Windows x64 (MinGW only)</li>
<li>Windows x86 (MSVC + MinGW)</li>
<li>Windows x86 (MinGW only)</li>
<li>Windows x86 "portable"</li>
<li>Linux x64 (Ubuntu 20.04)</li>
</ul>
<p>There is also a autoconf-enabled source package, to make building on Linux and MinGW easier.</p>
<p>A summary of new features and fixes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Changed cursor initialization (should fix <a class="issue-link js-issue-link" data-error-text="Failed to load title" data-id="1295941001" data-permission-text="Title is private" data-url="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/issues/88" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/mridoni/gixsql/issues/88/hovercard" href="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/issues/88">#88</a>)</li>
<li>Fix for "1.0.17/1.0.18 regression: COMMIT and ROLLBACK delete all cursor definitions -&gt; Status -111" (<a class="issue-link js-issue-link" data-error-text="Failed to load title" data-id="1355475097" data-permission-text="Title is private" data-url="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/issues/119" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/mridoni/gixsql/issues/119/hovercard" href="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/issues/119">#119</a>)</li>
<li>Merged pull request <a class="issue-link js-issue-link" data-error-text="Failed to load title" data-id="1402670500" data-permission-text="Title is private" data-url="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/issues/127" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/mridoni/gixsql/pull/127/hovercard" href="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/pull/127">#127</a> (thanks to Simon Sobisch)</li>
</ul>
<p>All the binary packages are available, as usual, on the corresponding <a href="https://github.com/mridoni/gixsql/releases/tag/v1.0.18b" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Release page on GitHub</a>.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
